{
  "reference_number": "11732",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "2050 seems a very casual date for responding to an existential catastrophe. Suggest 2035 or 2040. Every year we delay could mean\n the 2100s are an appalling century to live in, and the 2200s dead. (There is, as yet, no planet B). Aotearoa NZ is in a position to be a\n leader in how to bring down our carbon emissions (and a whole range of other pollutants, like plastics!) hard and fast; pay quite a lot\n\n now, but avoid far worse later... or at least make later more comfortable and survivable. We have the smart people, we have a stable\n system of government, we know the science, and we are building a social agreement; time to put some political capital and will into it!\n\n == The requirements of this sovereign \"saving our species\" action programme should over-ride any other obligations or\n impediments, such as arising from CPTPP and related/similar instruments."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "ASAP! 2035-2040. 2050 should be the target of last resort. All gases. Lots of other related pollutants. Do it fast; do it quick; make our\n grandchildren proud of us (if we keep going the way we are, they will not have any positive thoughts about us at all!)"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "No Outsourcing Our Problem! == No duck-shoving it off to someone else. == It's our country, and our mess. Sure: bring in overseas\n\n technology and expertise, but at the fundamental level, this is simply maths of a balanced biological/resource equation that, in a brief\n two centuries, we have whacked out of balance. == It's Our Responsibility To Re-establish Balance in our Biosphere."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, bring it forward from 2050 due to excellent progress."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "No. It is quite probably that, aside from earthquakes, natural events of such a scale to provide cause to interrupt the planned\nreductions will have been caused in part by the fact that we are sooooo late with the emissions and pollution reduction programme.\n\nSteel our resolve; stick to the plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the matters to account for, and also that the government objectives for climate change policy are sustainable economy,\nglobal and local leadership and creating a just and inclusive society bounded within a Tiriti o Waitangi partnership governance model."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "A great many environmental issues are inter-related. == * Rural: work with land-owners and users to reduce inputs and emissions,\n\nbut also change land-use patterns, rehabilitate our abused freshwater, de-stock to sustainable levels, promote organic and\npermacultural methods (giving us a price premium in overseas markets), retire marginal land to exotic and native forestry - perhaps\nmore exotic to start with in order to get the initial carbon-grab in the first 20 years, then a managed phase over to more and more\n\ndiverse native plantings - helping overall biodiversity (within a Predator Free framework). == [We own four small forestry blocks in both\nthe North and South Islands, one of which we are about to fell and so are considering the viabililty its future planting options.] == *\n\nUrban: work is in the form of diversified non-fossil/non-carbon fuelled energy sources, with a huge campaign to socialise a new form\nof urban living that is not beholden to the private car. The future can not afford continuation of private car ownership rates for a great\n\nmany reasons, irrespective the fuel type. Their presence requires too much land, resources, social, environmental and financial\nprivileging and subsidy, and has huge and diverse environmental impacts. People need to really take to heart \"Buy Local\", and grow\n\nlocal. Adapting to climate change impacts will require much greater local resilience and capability, so Regional Councils need their\nown carbon targets and mode shifting plans and targets to alleviate the need for people to own their own cars, and City Councils\nneed to wean themselves off the car-centric planning models and thing about new urban living patterns and forms. == Here in\n\nNaenae we are ourselves starting a long-term project to promote local community resilience by holding a community day where we\nwill recognise excellence and effort in at-home food production (Feb 23, 2019 if you're interested). While not explicit, it is in part to\n\nstart building local supply and reduce the suburb's dependence on supplies from Levin, which is not an easy ~90kms away."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes! With standing similar to the State Services Commission, i.e. un-ignorable!"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Remove the ETS from the politicians' control. They've proven unable to leave it alone. == People must be confronted with the costs\nof their activities that have until now been externalised to the environment. We must start paying the full costs of things, which that\nincludes environmental impact mitigation and clean-ups."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Local councils really need to keep their nga waka all going in similar directions, and having adaptation covered in law will really help,\n\nand reduce the costs of adapting."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Comprehensive, science-based - both hard and social science, socially aware."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely. We as a nation can't have some groups being able to play secret-squirrel with their insights and risk assessments. The\n\ntruth must out."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This response to the devastation our social and economic systems has inflicted on our planet is long past overdue. == Bold vision is\nneeded. == Firm decision making. == Inclusive actions, so we are all doing this together, not being done to by \"them\". == We must\nmove swiftly, and in ways that affirm our free participatory democracy and asserts our sovereign authority to make our own destiny.\n\n== Aotearoa New Zealand has a unique position in the world, and a unique opportunity we are in danger of squandering if we don't\nget on with it. == For the first time in Humanity's brief history: * we know about our world * we know about ourselves * we know what\n\nwe can do * we know we need to change if we as a species are to become the true custodians and stewards of our precious planet's\nnga taonga. == Let's Do This."
    }
  ]
}
